A Guide to the Margaret Ethel Kelley Kern Papers, 1895-1949
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Margaret Ethel Kelley Kern Papers, 1895-1949
The Library of Virginia
23481
9.5 cubic feet (20 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Margaret Ethel Kelley Kern, Richmond.
Biographical Information
Margaret Ethel Kelley Kern was born 13 February 1874. She did volunteer work during World War I, serving with various organizations, including the National League for Women's Service, Godmothers' League, War Camp Community Service Woman's Auxiliary, and the Service Legion. She also wrote articles for numerous periodicals, and is the author of The Trail of the Three Notched Road. She was also served as information officer for the Virginia State Chamber of Commerce. She married Dr. George Thomas Walker Kern (1873-1948), and they had one daughter. Kern died 10 July 1975 in Richmond, Virginia, and is buried in Hollywood Cemetery.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1895-1949, of Margaret Ethel Kelley Kern (1874-1975) of Richmond, Virginia, relating to her work with various patriotic and relief organizations during World War I, including the National League for Women's Service, Godmother's League, War Camp Community Service, and the Service Legion, focusing especially on her work at the hospitals at Camp Lee and the U.S. Army Debarkation Hospital No. 52 at Richmond College. There is also information regarding her involvement in the Powhatan Hill Memorial Association, Thomas Jefferson National Memorial Association, and the United Daughters of the Confederacy. The collection contains articles, constitutions and by-laws, commissions, correspondence, greeting cards, guidebooks, invitations, lists, magazines, newsletters, notebooks, pamphlets, photographs, postcards, posters, publications, reports, and scrapbooks. There is a good deal of correspondence with Major General Adelbert Cronkhite (1861-1937), and also information concerning her efforts to preserve portions of Camp Lee, and the establishment of a war memorial in Richmond. Of particular note are drafts and chapters of a book Kern intended to publish on her war activities, and Richmond during World War I (Box 16). There is also material relating to her book The Trail of the Three Notched Road.
Contents List
- Correspondence, 1895. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1903. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1907. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1908. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1909. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1910. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1911. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1912. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1913. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1914. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1915. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1916. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1917. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1918 (January-June). (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1918 (July-December). (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1919 (January-June). (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 1919 (July-December). (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Correspondence, 1920. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Correspondence, 1921. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1922 (January-June). (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1922 (July-December). (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1923 (January-February). (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1923 (March). (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1923 (April-September). (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1923 (October-December). (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1924 (January-February). (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1924 (March). (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1924 (April-June). (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1924 (July-December). (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1925. (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1926. (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1927. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1928. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1929. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1930. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1931. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1932 (January-August). (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1932 (September-December). (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1933 (January-June). (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1933 (July-December). (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1934. (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1935. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1936 (January-May). (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1936 (June-December). (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1937. (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1938. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1939. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1940. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1941. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1942. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1943. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1944. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1945. (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1948. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, n.d.. (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
- Agriculture School. (Box 4, Folder 12)
- "America First". (Box 4, Folder 13-14)
- American Commission for Relief in Belgium. (Box 4, Folder 15)
- American Committee for Devastated France. (Box 4, Folder 16)
- American Committee for Relief in the Near East. (Box 4, Folder 17)
- American Legion. (Box 4, Folder 18)
- American Relief Clearing House. (Box 4, Folder 19)
- American Women's Hospitals. (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Anderson Gallery of Art, 1931-1932. (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Are You Dedicated?. (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Articles Written by M. Ethel Kelley Kern. (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
- Bail Bond of Jefferson Davis (Facsimile). (Box 20)
- The Bayonet (Camp Lee). (Box 20)
- The Beckoning Land by E. Alexander Powell. (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Belgravia War Hospital Supply Depot Monthly Record, September 1918. (Box 20)
- Bell Tavern Memorial Tablet. (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Biltmore House and Gardens. (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Biographical. (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Bonus Expeditionary Force, 1932. (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Boy Scouts. (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Byrd, Harry F.. (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Camp Lee - Described and Photographed by Richard Batchelder, 1918. (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Camp Lee Hospital Visit with Mrs. Westmoreland Davis. (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Camp Lee Remembrance Book. (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Capitol Square Memorial Tree, 1930. (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Carillon Dedication Program, 1932. (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Cartoons - Peter Arno. (Box 5, Folder 15)
- The Case of Major-General Adelbert Cronkhite. (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Chemical Exhibit, Smithsonian. (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Clark, Allan N.. (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Clippings. (Box 5, Folder 19-20)
- Clippings. (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
- College of William and Mary - Historical Notes. (Box 6, Folder 3)
- The Come-Back, 11 January 1919. (Box 20)
- Commissions. (Box 20)
- Committee on Public Information. (Box 6, Folder 4)
- The Common Cause: Britain's Part in the Great War. (Box 6, Folder 5)
- The Commonwealth, 1937-1939. (Box 18)
- Community Songs. (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Confederate Memorial Institute. (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Council of National Defense, Virginia Division. (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Daughters of the American Revolution. (Box 6, Folder 9)
- D.W. Griffith Presents America. (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Deportation of Alien Criminals, etc. - Hearings, 1926. (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Eightieth Division Veterans Association. (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Ephemera. (Box 19)
- Fatherless Children of France. (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Ferdinand Foch Visit, 1921. (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Ferdinand Foch Memorial Service, 1929. (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Flag. (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Food Conservation Registration, July 1917. (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Food Conservation Registration Poster. (Box 20)
- Food for France Fund. (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Forty Years with the Virginia Division United Daughters of the Confederacy by Mrs. Cabell Smith. (Box 6, Folder 19)
- 41 Places and Subjects in Alexandria, Virginia. (Box 6, Folder 20)
- The Founding of a Nation, 1607-1919. (Box 6, Folder 21)
- Freeman, Douglas Southall. (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Garden Week, 1932-1938. (Box 7, Folder 1)
- The Game of Life As We Are Playing it in Our Archaic Industrial System by John J. Lanier, 1934. (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Genealogy. (Box 7, Folder 3)
- General Federation of Women's Clubs. (Box 7, Folder 4)
- A General Survey of the Virginia Peninsula, 1938. (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Girl Scouts. (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Goddin's Tavern. (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Godmothers' League - Minutes. (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Godmothers' League - Miscellaneous. (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Godmothers' League - Scrapbook. (Box 7, Folder 10-12)
- Greeting Cards. (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Guidebook - St. Petersburg, Florida. (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Guidebook - State of Washington. (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Heads Up, 1918 (December). (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Heads Up, 1919 (January). (Box 7, Folder 17)
- Heads Up, 1919 (February). (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Heads Up, 1919 (March). (Box 7, Folder 19)
- Heads Up, 1919 (April). (Box 7, Folder 20)
- Heads Up - Original Cartoons. (Box 20)
- Historical Information for Signs at County Lines. (Box 7, Folder 21)
- History of the Fire and Police Departments of Richmond, Virginia. (Box 7, Folder 22)
- Homecoming Celebration - 29th and 80th Divisions. (Box 7, Folder 23)
- Housewives League. (Box 7, Folder 24)
- Inaugural Program - Gov. H.C. Stuart, 1914. (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Interiors of Virginia Houses of Colonial Times by Edith Tunis Sale. (Box 8, Folder 2-4)
- Invitations. (Box 8, Folder 5-6)
- Jackson Memorial Wildflower Preserve, Chancellorsville. (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Jubilee Week, 1919. (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Kern County, California. (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Knitting. (Box 8, Folder 10)
- La Petite Gironde, 23 January 1918. (Box 20)
- League of Nations Non-Partisan Association. (Box 8, Folder 11)
- League of Women Voters. (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Liberty Loans/Liberty Bonds. (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Library War Council. (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Lincoln, Abraham. (Box 8, Folder 15)
- The Literary Digest, 15 April 1933. (Box 8, Folder 16)
- MacNeill, Rev. Allan. (Box 8, Folder 17)
- Martinet, Jeanne. (Box 8, Folder 18-19)
- Martinet, Jeanne. (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
- Medical College of Virginia Base Hospital No. 45 - Newsletter, 5 November 1917. (Box 20)
- Membership Cards and Dues. (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Memorial Wreaths. (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Military Order of the World War. (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Miller & Rhoades Golden Jubilee, 1935. (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Miscellaneous. (Box 9, Folder 7-8)
- National Americanization Committee. (Box 9, Folder 9)
- National Civic Federation. (Box 9, Folder 10)
- National Committee of Patriotic Societies. (Box 9, Folder 11)
- National League of American Pen Women. (Box 9, Folder 12)
- National League for Woman's Service. (Box 9, Folder 13)
- National League for Woman's Service, Capital City Division. (Box 9, Folder 14)
- National Pledge Card Campaign, 21-27 October 1917. (Box 9, Folder 15)
- National Pledge Card Campaign, 21-27 October 1917. (Box 20)
- National Recovery Administration. (Box 9, Folder 16)
- National Star Spangled Banner Centennial, 1914. (Box 20)
- National Surgical Dressings Committee. (Box 9, Folder 17)
- National Tobacco Festival - South Boston, 2-3 September 1937. (Box 9, Folder 18)
- National Victory Memorial Building, Washington. (Box 9, Folder 19)
- National War Garden Commission. (Box 10, Folder 1)
- National Woman's Liberty Loan Committee. (Box 10, Folder 2)
- National Women's Trade Union League. (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Natural Bridge. (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Notebook - Godmothers' League. (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Notebooks. (Box 10, Folder 6-7)
- Occidental Restaurant. (Box 10, Folder 8)
- One Hundred Years of Peace. (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Our War President (Woodrow Wilson). (Box 20)
- Pensions and National Health in Canada, 1936. (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Permanent Blind Relief War Fund. (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Photograph (Rolled) - Army Nurse Corps, Debarkation Hospital No. 52. (Box 19)
- Photographs. (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Pointed Paragraphs on War of 1812. (Box 10, Folder 13)
- Portrait Exhibition, Virginia House, 1929. (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Postcards. (Box 10, Folder 15)
- Powhatan's Hill Marker Dedication. (Box 10, Folder 16-17)
- Presidential Stamp Album. (Box 10, Folder 18)
- Programs. (Box 10, Folder 19)
- Reclamation Service. (Box 10, Folder 20)
- Red Cross. (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
- Report of War Activities (Richmond Public Schools), 1917-1918. (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Report of War Activities, 1918-1919. (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Reserve City Bankers Association Meeting, 1931. (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Richmond Bicentennial, 1936-1937. (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Richmond Bicentennial - Richmond News-Leader Supplement. (Box 20)
- Richmond Chamber of Commerce. (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Richmond Department of Public Utitlities - Annual Report, 1936. (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Richmond Light Infantry Blues. (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Richmond Magazine. (Box 11, Folder 10)
- Richmond War History Commission Honor Roll. (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Richmond War History Commission - Reports of Volunteer Organizations. (Box 11, Folder 12)
- Richmond War Library Committee. (Box 11, Folder 13)
- Richmond Water Supply. (Box 20)
- Road Maps. (Box 11, Folder 14)
- Roadside Development. (Box 11, Folder 15)
- The Roanoke of Colonial Days by F.B. Kegley. (Box 11, Folder 16)
- The Romance and Renaissance of the College of William and Mary in Virginia. (Box 11, Folder 17)
- Romanian Relief Committee of America. (Box 11, Folder 18)
- Sale, Mrs. William Wilson. (Box 11, Folder 19)
- Scuffletown Tavern. (Box 11, Folder 20)
- Scrapbook - "Laugh and Learn". (Box 11, Folder 21)
- Scrapbook - National Industrial Recovery Act. (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
- Selective Service Regulations, 1918. (Box 18)
- Serbian Relief Committee of America. (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Service Legion - Accounts and Receipts. (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Service Legion - Annual Reports. (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Service Legion - Certificate of Incorporation. (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Service Legion - Constitution and By-Laws. (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Service Legion - 80th Division Reunion Punch Fund. (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Service Legion - Fifth Annual Luncheon, 7 April 1924. (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Service Legion - Gold Star Flag. (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Service Legion - History. (Box 12, Folder 11)
- Service Legion - Memorial Boulder Fund. (Box 12, Folder 12)
- Service Legion - Memorial Cross. (Box 12, Folder 13)
- Service Legion - Memorial Flower Fund. (Box 12, Folder 14)
- Service Legion - Minutes. (Box 12, Folder 15)
- Service Legion - Miscellaneous. (Box 12, Folder 16)
- Service Legion - Monroe Parade. (Box 12, Folder 17)
- Service Legion - Resolutions. (Box 12, Folder 18)
- Service Legion - Three Days for the Blind. (Box 12, Folder 19)
- Service Legion - War Memorial (Riverview Cemetery). (Box 12, Folder 20)
- Service Legion - Wilson, Woodrow. (Box 12, Folder 21)
- The Service Magazine. (Box 18)
- Sievers, F. William. (Box 12, Folder 22)
- The Sixteen Immortals. (Box 13, Folder 1)
- The Song of the Seventy Five by Grantland Rice. (Box 20)
- Southern Literary Messenger. (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Spring Street Home. (Box 13, Folder 3)
- The Story of Virginia Products That Excel. (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Suffrage. (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Sympathy Letters and Notes. (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Superintendent of Public Instruction - Annual Report, 1935-1936. (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Thomas Jefferson National Memorial Association. (Box 13, Folder 8-12)
- Thomas Jefferson National Memorial Association - Minute Book. (Box 13, Folder 13)
- Three Chopt Road Name Change. (Box 13, Folder 14)
- Thrift Stamp/War Savings Stamp Poster. (Box 20)
- Tickets. (Box 13, Folder 15)
- To the Homeward-Bound Americans by B. Van Vorst. (Box 13, Folder 16)
- Tobacco Growing in Virginia. (Box 13, Folder 17)
- Treat'em Square, December 1921. (Box 13, Folder 18)
- Treatment of Burns. (Box 13, Folder 19)
- The Trail of the Three Notched Road, 1927. (Box 13, Folder 20)
- The Trail of the Three Notched Road, 1928 (January-September). (Box 13, Folder 21)
- The Trail of the Three Notched Road, 1928 (October-December). (Box 13, Folder 22)
- The Trail of the Three Notched Road, 1929 (January-July). (Box 13, Folder 23)
- The Trail of the Three Notched Road, 1929 (August-December). (Box 14, Folder 1)
- The Trail of the Three Notched Road, 1930-1931. (Box 14, Folder 2)
- The Trail of the Three Notched Road - Clippings and Reviews. (Box 14, Folder 3)
- The Trail of the Three Notched Road - Draft. (Box 14, Folder 4)
- The Trail of the Three Notched Road - Poster. (Box 20)
- The Trail of the Three Notched Road - Sales and Orders. (Box 14, Folder 5)
- The Trail of the Three Notched Road - William Byrd Press. (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Trinity Parish, Staunton. (Box 14, Folder 7)
- Turman, Dr. John. (Box 14, Folder 8)
- Tyler, Lyon G.. (Box 14, Folder 9)
- The Union Herald. (Box 14, Folder 10)
- United Daughters of the Confederacy. (Box 14, Folder 11)
- United Daughters of the Confederacy - Scrapbook. (Box 14, Folder 12-14)
- United States Chamber of Commerce. (Box 14, Folder 15)
- United States Department of Agriculture. (Box 14, Folder 16)
- United States Employment Service. (Box 14, Folder 17)
- United States Food Administration. (Box 14, Folder 18)
- United States Good Roads Association. (Box 14, Folder 19)
- United States School Garden Army. (Box 14, Folder 20)
- Vacation Savings Fund Stamps. (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Vacation War Relief Committee. (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Valentine, Edward V.. (Box 15, Folder 3)
- Veterans of Foreign Wars. (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Virgnia's Armistice Celebration. (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Virginia Democrats/Byrd Luncheon. (Box 15, Folder 6)
- Virginia First by Lyon G. Tyler. (Box 15, Folder 7)
- Virginia: First in the Heart of the Nation. (Box 18)
- Virginia Flag and Seal. (Box 15, Folder 8)
- Virginia Gazette. (Box 20)
- The Virginia Guardsman. (Box 15, Folder 9)
- Virginia Good Roads Association. (Box 15, Folder 10)
- Virginia Guidebooks. (Box 15, Folder 11-13)
- Virginia Historical Society. (Box 15, Folder 14)
- Virginia League of Fine Arts and Handicrafts. (Box 15, Folder 15)
- Virginia State Chamber of Commerce. (Box 15, Folder 16-17)
- Virginia State Chamber of Commerce - Newsletters. (Box 15, Folder 18-19)
- Virginia State Chamber of Commerce - Reports of the Information Secretary. (Box 15, Folder 20)
- Virginia Tobacco by Roy C. Flannagan. (Box 15, Folder 21)
- Virginia War History Commission. (Box 15, Folder 22)
- Virginia War History Commission - Newsletters. (Box 20)
- Vocal Lessons. (Box 15, Folder 23)
- Wakefield National Memorial Association. (Box 15, Folder 24)
- War Book. (Box 16, Folder 1-12)
- War Kitchen. (Box 17, Folder 1)
- War Loan Organization. (Box 17, Folder 2)
- War Memorial. (Box 17, Folder 3-5)
- War Relief Association of Virginia. (Box 17, Folder 6)
- Watering the City of Richmond, 1930. (Box 17, Folder 7)
- Westmoreland Club Officers' Dances. (Box 17, Folder 8)
- Woman's Constitutional League of Virginia. (Box 17, Folder 9)
- Woman's Auxiliary, American Legion. (Box 17, Folder 10)
- Woman's Auxiliary, American Legion - Constitution and By-Laws. (Box 17, Folder 11)
- Woman's Auxiliary, War Camp Community Service - Minutes. (Box 17, Folder 12)
- Woman's Auxiliary, War Camp Community Service - Miscellaneous. (Box 17, Folder 13)
- Woman's Auxiliary, War Camp Community Service - Register. (Box 17)
- Woman's Homecoming Committee. (Box 17, Folder 14)
- Woman's Land Army of America. (Box 17, Folder 15)
- Woman's Naval Service. (Box 17, Folder 16)
- Women and Preparedness. (Box 17, Folder 17)
- Women as Munitions Makers. (Box 17, Folder 18)
- Wood, Gov. James - Biography. (Box 17, Folder 19)
- Woodrow Wilson Memorial Service, 6 February 1924. (Box 17, Folder 20)
- A Word-Picturelogue Thru Beautiful Historic Charlottesville, 1928. (Box 17, Folder 21)
- YMCA. (Box 17, Folder 22)
- YWCA. (Box 17, Folder 23)
- Yorktown Sesquicentennial Association/Commission. (Box 17, Folder 24)